<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="guide.css"?>
<book xml:id="guide" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" lang="en">
    <title>MobilityDB Hiking Workshop</title>
    <info>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Alice</firstname>
                <surname>Lombard</surname>
            </personname>
        </author>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Raphaël</firstname>
                <surname>Dubuget</surname>
            </personname>
        </author>
        <pubdate>July 2024</pubdate>
    </info>

    <section xml:id="intro">
        <para>
            This document is an example of how you can use MobilityDB in order to analyse data. It is directly inspired by 
            the <ulink url="https://mobilitydb.github.io/MobilityDB-workshop/develop/html/index.html">MobilityDB Workshop</ulink> already existing. 
            We will throughout this document present different use cases of MobilityDB, which is an extension on PostGIS and PostgreSQL. 
        </para>       
        <para>
            This workshop was made by two students from <ulink url="https://www.insa-rennes.fr/index.html">INSA Rennes</ulink> during an internship in June, July and August 2024. 
        </para>
        <para>
            We will use data from <ulink url="https://www.openstreetmap.org/user/atchisson/traces">OpenStreetMap</ulink>. The traces we are going to use in this example are rando_morbi1.gpx and rando_morbi2.gpx.<sbr/>
            GPX is a common file format for storing GPS data. It is used by many GPS devices and applications to store track logs and waypoints. In our case, a person did two hikes on the 26th of June 2024, in the Morbihan, and saved the data in two GPX files.<sbr />
            Then, this person exported the data to OpenStreetMap and we can use his trace as we want. We will use these GPX files in this workshop.<sbr />
            Please download the files<ulink url="https://www.openstreetmap.org/user/atchisson/traces/11390305"> rando_morbi1.gpx</ulink> and <ulink url="https://www.openstreetmap.org/user/atchisson/traces/11390306">rando_morbi2.gpx</ulink> from the OpenStreetMap website and put in a folder you will remember.
        </para>       
        <para>
            Now, we are ready to start the workshop.<sbr/>
            While this workshop illustrates the usage of MobilityDB functions, it does not explain them in detail. 
            If you need help concerning the functions of MobilityDB, please 
            refer to the <ulink url="https://mobilitydb.com/documentation.html">documentation</ulink>. 
        </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="chapter1">
        <title>Chapitre 1: SQL work</title>

        <section xml:id="part11">
        <title>Importing the data</title>

        <para>
            Blabla this is Raph's work
        </para>       
        </section>

    </section>
    <section xml:id="chapter2">
        <title>Chapitre 2: Visualizing the data</title>

        <section xml:id="part21">
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <para>
            Now, we have cleaned the data and made it ready to be used. We will now visualize the data in order to have a better understanding of it.<sbr/>
            To do so, we are going to use QGIS, a free and open-source geographic information system. You can download it TODO<ulink url="https://qgis.org/en/site/forusers/download.html">here</ulink>.<sbr/>
        </para>       
        </section>

    </section>
</book>
