<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="JSON">
    <title>GBFS data (applicable for every JSON data)</title>
    <para>    
        We will, for our examples, use data from STAR which is the Rennes' public transport company (<ulink url="https://data.rennesmetropole.fr/explore/dataset/vls-gbfs-tr/table/?dataChart=eyJxdWVyaWVzIjpbeyJjb25maWciOnsiZGF0YXNldCI6InZscy1nYmZzLXRyIiwib3B0aW9ucyI6e319LCJjaGFydHMiOlt7ImFsaWduTW9udGgiOnRydWUsInR5cGUiOiJjb2x1bW4iLCJmdW5jIjoiQ09VTlQiLCJzY2llbnRpZmljRGlzcGxheSI6dHJ1ZSwiY29sb3IiOiIjNjZjMmE1In1dLCJ4QXhpcyI6ImlkZmlsZWdiZnMiLCJtYXhwb2ludHMiOjUwLCJzb3J0IjoiIn1dLCJ0aW1lc2NhbGUiOiIiLCJkaXNwbGF5TGVnZW5kIjp0cnVlLCJhbGlnbk1vbnRoIjp0cnVlfQ%3D%3D">link</ulink>). 
        This data is protected by ODbL (Open Database License): Data source: STAR Data Explore/Rennes Métropole.
    </para>
    <section>
        <title>Presentation</title>
        <para>
            The General Bikeshare Feed Specification (GBFS) is a data format that is used to provide real-time information about the status of a bike-sharing system. 
            It is various JSON files that contain information about the stations, the bikes, the status of the stations, the status of the bikes, etc...
            <sbr/>Among them, we can find the following files:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        gbfs.json: Root file describing all the files used in the STAR bike share system's use of the GBFS standard.
                        It is updated every minute. We didn't collect data for 1 week, because data doesn't significally change.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        station_information.json: List of stations in STAR's bike sharing network, their capacities, locations and geolocations.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        system_regions.json: STAR bike share application region.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        system_alerts.json: Alerts and unavailabilities for stations in the STAR bike share network.
                        It is updated every minute. We collected data for 1 week, using a script in the repository.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        system_information.json: General information about STAR bike share (organization, contact, e-mail, website).
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        system_hours.json: STAR bike share opening hours.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        system_calendar.json: STAR bike share opening days.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        station_status.json: Information on available services, bike availability and locations for each station in the STAR bike share network.
                        We collected data for 1 week.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        free_bike_status.json: List of bikes available for hire throughout the STAR bike sharing network.
                        We collected data for 1 week.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        system_pricing_plans.json: STAR bike sharing tariffs and subscriptions (Summary version).
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>